Guide to the Jacques Reich Portrait Prints, 1890–1923, undated PR 102
New-York Historical Society
Jacques Reich portrait prints
1890–1923, undated
New-York Historical Society
Reich, Jacques, 1852-1923
PR 102
115 item(s) in 9 folders.
Portraits of major American and European artists, writers, capitalists, politicians, and historical figures executed by Jacques Reich (1852–1923), a Hungarian-born artist who moved to the United States in 1873. In addition to privately commissioned portraits, Reich executed some 2,000 illustrations for Appletons' Cyclopædia of American Biography, and created most of those in Scribner's Cyclopedia of Painters and Paintings.
Arrangement
Prints are sorted physically by size in 9 folders, 5 small and 4 large. The container list provides alphabetical access by sitter.
Biographical note
Jacques Reich (1852–1923) was a Hungarian-born portrait etcher who immigrated to the United States in 1873. He trained for several years at the National Academy of Design in New York and at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in Philadelphia before traveling to Paris in 1879 to study under the painters William-Adolphe Bouguereau and Joseph Nicolas Robert-Fleury. He returned to Philadelphia in 1880, and in 1885 moved to New York, where he established a studio. In addition to pen and ink drawings for magazines and other publications, Reich created some 2,000 portraits for Appletons' Cyclopædia of American Biography, and most of the portraits for Scribner's Cyclopedia of Painters and Paintings. He later specialized in etchings on copper, and in this medium published portraits of notable authors, poets, artists, and famous Americans, as well as private commissions for Whitelaw Reid, H. H. Rogers, E. H. Harriman, Charles B. Alexander, John W. Mackay, Nelson W. Aldrich. After his marriage to Caroline Bellinger in 1892, Reich resided in New Dorp, Staten Island. He died there on July 8, 1923.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Oswald D. Reich, 1973, 1974, 1975. New-York Historical Society staff assigned the following numbers to the items in each accession: 1–93 (1973), 94–106 (1974), and 107–115 (1975).
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society's Manuscript Collection holds a series of letters received, with a few replies, of Jacques Reich, dated 1887–1923. Most letters relate to his etchings done for publication and for private commissions, and to the pen and ink portraits he executed for Appletons' Cyclopædia of American Biography and Scribner's Cyclopedia of Painters and Paintings. Among Reich's correspondents are Grover Cleveland, Frederick Dent Grant, Daniel Huntington, Robert Todd Lincoln, and James Russell Lowell. Call phrase: J. Reich Papers.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains portraits etched by Jacques Reich during the period 1890–1923 of major American and European artists, writers, capitalists, politicians, and historical figures. These include United States presidents George Washington, James Madison, Andrew Jackson, Abraham Lincoln, Ulysses S. Grant, Grover Cleveland, William McKinley, Theodore Roosevelt, William Howard Taft, Woodrow Wilson, and Warren G. Harding. Writers and artists pictured include Ralph Waldo Emerson, Washington Irving, Edgar Allen Poe, Harriet Beecher Stowe, James McNeill Whistler, and John Greenleaf Whittier. Other portraits include Nelson Aldrich, John Jacob Astor, William Cullen Bryant, Andrew Carnegie, Adna Chaffee, Henry Clay, Benjamin Franklin, Alexander Hamilton, John Paul Jones, Robert E. Lee, John Marshall, J. P. Morgan, William Penn, Frank Stockton, and Daniel Webster. Several prints have notations or documentation identifying the photographs or paintings from which they were engraved.
Artists.; Etchers; Portraitists.; Printmakers.; Authors -- Portraits.; Legislators -- United States -- Portraits.; Presidents -- United States -- Portraits.; Artists' proofs.; Etchings (prints); Portraits.; Prints (visual works); Remarque proofs.; Self-portraits.; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915 -- Portraits; Astor, John Jacob, 1864-1912 -- Portraits; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878 -- Portraits; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919 -- Portraits; Chaffee, Adna Romanza, 1842-1914 -- Portraits; Clay, Henry, 1849-1884 -- Portraits; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908 -- Portraits; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882 -- Portraits; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 -- Portraits; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885 -- Portraits; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 -- Portraits; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923 -- Portraits; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859 -- Portraits; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845 -- Portraits; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870 -- Portraits; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Portraits; Madison, James, 1751-1836 -- Portraits; Marshall, John, 1755-1835 -- Portraits; McKinley, William, 1843-1901 -- Portraits; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913 -- Portraits; Penn, William, 1644-1718 -- Portraits; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849 -- Portraits; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919 -- Portraits; Stockton, Frank R., 1834-1902 -- Portraits; Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896 -- Portraits; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930 -- Portraits; Washington, George, 1732-1799 -- Portraits; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852. -- Portraits; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903 -- Portraits; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1882 -- Portraits; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924 -- Portraits
- Portraits by Jacques Reich, 1890–1923, undated
  - Aldrich, Nelson, Senator, 1917 (Folder Large-1)
  - Alexander the Great, 1902 (Folder Small-1)
  - Alexander, Charles Beatty (5 prints), 1917 (Folder Large-1)
  - Andrews, Charles, 1898 (Folder Large-1)
  - Astor, John Jacob, Colonel (2 prints), undated (Folder Small-1)
  - Beekman, Gerard, 1920 (Folder Large-1)
  - Brady, Anthony M., 1907 (Folder Small-1)
  - Bryant, William Cullen, 1899 (Folder Large-1)
  - Carnegie, Andrew, 1906 (Folder Large-1)
  - Carter, Walter S., 1897 (Folder Large-1)
  - Catherine the Great (2 prints), 1902, undated (Folder Small-1)
  - Chaffee, Adna, General (2 prints), 1914, undated (Folder Small-1)
  - Charles V (2 prints), 1902, undated (Folder Small-1)
  - Choate, Joseph, 1896 (Folder Large-1)
  - Clark (2 prints), 1911, undated (Folder Small-2)
  - Clay, Henry, 1896 (Folder Large-2)
  - Cleveland, Grover, 1906 (Folder Large-2)
  - Cook, Charles, undated (Folder Small-2)
  - Crandall, F. W., 1904 (Folder Small-2)
  - Curtis, George William, 1907 (Folder Large-2)
  - Dickens, Charles, 1890 (Folder Small-2)
  - Douglas, John, Dr., 1918 (Folder Large-2)
  - Dwight, M. E., Rev., 1907 (Folder Small-2)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (2 prints), 1899, 1921 (Folder Small-2)
  - Franklin, Benjamin, 1903 (Folder Large-2)
  - Garrison, Lloyd McKim, undated (Folder Small-2)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., 1908 (Folder Large-2)
  - Hamilton, Alexander, 1903 (Folder Large-2)
  - Hanna, Mark, Senator, 1904 (Folder Large-2)
  - Harding, Warren G., 1922 (Folder Large-2)
  - Henry, Patrick, 1916 (Folder Large-2)
  - Hubbard, General, 1917 (Folder Large-2)
  - Irving, Washington, 1902 (Folder Small-2)
  - Jackson, Andrew, 1908 (Folder Large-2)
  - Jefferson, Joseph, undated (Folder Small-2)
  - Jones, John Paul, 1905 (Folder Large-2)
  - Kane, Elisha Kent, 1900 (Folder Small-5)
  - King, Charles, General (2 prints), 1914, undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Kock, Paul de, 1902 (Folder Small-2)
  - Kossuth, Louis, 1894 (Folder Large-3)
  - Lee, Robert E., 1913 (Folder Large-3)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, 1907 (Folder Small-3)
  - Lincoln and his Lieutenants, 1911 (Folder Large-3)
  - Liscum, E. H., Col., 1902 (Folder Large-3)
  - Lowell, James Russell, 1899 (Folder Large-3)
  - Luther, Martin (2 prints), 1902, undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Mackay, John, 1912 (Folder Large-3)
  - Madison, James, 1911 (Folder Large-3)
  - Marshall, John, 1909 (Folder Large-3)
  - McKinley, William (2 prints), 1902, 1905 (Folder Large-3)
  - Meredith, George, 1909 (Folder Small-3)
  - Morgan, J. Pierpont (small), 1905 (Folder Small-3)
  - Morgan, J. Pierpont (large), 1904 (Folder Large-3)
  - Napoleon (2 prints), 1902, undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Palmer, Potter, 1903 (Folder Small-3)
  - Penfield, Frederick C., Ambassador, 1923 (Folder Large-4)
  - Penn, William, 1902 (Folder Small-3)
  - Perkins, George W., 1921 (Folder Large-4)
  - Perkins, Simon III, 1914 (Folder Large-4)
  - Poe, Edgar Allan, 1919 (Folder Large-4)
  - Reich, Jacques, undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Richelieu, Cardinal, undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Rogers, H. H., 1910 (Folder Large-4)
  - Roosa, Daniel Bennett St. John, 1908 (Folder Small-3)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (small), undated (Folder Small-3)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (large), 1919 (Folder Large-4)
  - Ropes, John C., 1908 (Folder Small-3)
  - Russell, Lord, 1897 (Folder Large-4)
  - Schmidlapp, Jacob G., 1920 (Folder Large-4)
  - Severance, Louis, 1915 (Folder Large-4)
  - Stanton, John C., 1908 (Folder Small-4)
  - Sterling, John W., 1918 (Folder Large-4)
  - Stevens, Mrs., undated (Folder Large-4)
  - Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1909 (Folder Large-4)
  - Stockton, Frank, 1903 (Folder Small-4)
  - Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1898 (Folder Large-4)
  - Taft, William Howard, 1910 (Folder Large-4)
  - Tennyson, Alfred, 1899 (Folder Large-4)
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1907 (Folder Large-4)
  - Tileston, Thomas (2 prints), undated (Folder Small-4)
  - Tracy, D. W. D., 1913 (Folder Small-4)
  - Van Brunt, Charles H., Chief Justice, 1897 (Folder Large-4)
  - Vespucci, Amerigo, 1902 (Folder Small-4)
  - Vreeland, H. H., 1906 (Folder Small-4)
  - Wagner, Richard, 1911 (Folder Large-4)
  - Washington, George, 1902 (Folder Large-4)
  - Webster, Daniel, 1904 (Folder Large-4)
  - Wellington, Duke of [Arthur Wellesley], 1902 (Folder Small-4)
  - Whistler, James McNeill, 1916 (Folder Large-4)
  - White, Andrew D., 1918 (Folder Small-5)
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf (2 prints), 1899 (Folder Large-4)
  - Wilkie bookplate, 1896 (Folder Small-4)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (small; 2 prints), 1914 (Folder Small-4)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (large; 2 prints), 1917 (Folder Large-4)
  - Unidentified, undated (Folder Small-4)
  - "Etched Portraits of Famous Americans and of Poets, Authors & Musicians", undated (Folder Small-5)
    Scope and Contents
    Reich's self-published catalog.